uh so we're going to continue with the
medicine Buddha uh yesterday we talked
about uh how we had already
covered uh the general practices for
meditating and we covered the seven
preliminaries which is a bad name
because one of them is not a preliminary
okay uh but it's okay and now we're
going to cover the second part uh that's
preliminary are kind of a preparation on
the outside of yourself and now we're
going to do a preparation on the inside
of yourself okay so we have itm 5.8
which is a lady going like
this okay and that represents uh
preparing on the
inside uh for the medicine Bo practice
okay uh why I show these pictures is
that later I'm going to test you on the
pictures and if you can't tell me what a
picture is you have to give me back the
$100 okay so that's why I make a
profit okay Teddy's getting serious okay
he's
like okay anyway she's preparing on the
inside okay and here's a list of things
that we'll be doing during our Retreat
to prepare on the in next slide you
guys yeah uh we're going to commit to
the one day
vow uh the main purpose of the one day
vow is
dieting many many Buddhist people who
are
overweight uh changed their life habit
from doing the one day V I'm just
kidding but it's true okay and I saw it
for many many years okay my my teacher
used to give the one day vows pretty
frequently and um it breaks your eating
habits okay and it's a nice it's a nice
thing uh the the parts of the one day
vow you're not supposed to eat uh
afternoon or you're not supposed
to uh do a lot of the things that you
normally do are just to remind you okay
you feel hungry and you say why do I
feel hungry and then it's to remind you
that you are especially keeping your
morality that day very strictly okay the
10 the 10 Good Deeds especially uh you
are trying to keep them very strictly
that day so you're more careful not to
exaggerate like the Michael does or uh
you know on that day you're more careful
to be a good person uh and not to hurt
other people those vows are famous the
mainly eight different commitments
that uh they're very famous
for of the first level of Buddhist
morality which is not hurting other
people what's the second
level second level is bodh morality
where where you actually try to help
people so the first level of morality is
you know minimum please try not to hurt
other people okay don't lie don't steal
uh like that and then the second level
of Buddhist morality is try to do
something to help other people and
that's that's a higher that's a higher
level of morality okay uh especially try
to help them get to Enlightenment as I
mentioned my wife is uh late yesterday
because a friend of hers is dying in
Tucson and
uh I I don't know if she died last night
but they you know it's a what do you
call it
it's poignant it's sad you know they
they know she's dying and they can't do
nobody can do anything all they can do
is try to guess what time she's going to
die and her children she has young
children and she has a husband and you
know there's
nothing to do for them
nobody they did a what do you call
GoFundMe for the hospital expenses which
is like the only way most people can pay
it and um
nobody wrote me and said can she stay
alive can you keep her alive and it's
not you cannot do that right so there's
a higher the second morality is higher
because you're trying to save people
from Death okay and then I was uh
teaching in Peru uh a couple weeks ago
nice place it's a business college
called essan and they had 16 I heard it
was 1600 people
and uh the organizer had a dream that he
should invite the military and I'm like
you sure and he's like yeah and he
invited the military and we had like a
hundred officers in white uniforms and
it was very beautiful and they're all
excited they're asking us to come back
next year the military uh wants us to do
a program for 3,000 people or something
uh so we were uh we were giving that
talk there and the president of the
University had us for breakfast and he
asked
us how do you describe Buddhist morality
what's Buddhist ethics and I said three
levels one don't you know don't hurt
other people which is the one day V is
supposed to be that secondly try to help
other people and what's the third
one
huh yeah but what's the main I mean if
we say don't hurt other people help
other people
and do it fast okay do it fast like help
them within one life okay so that's
really the difference of the three kinds
of morality uh the one day vow
emphasizes don't hurt other beings don't
kill don't steal don't hurt other
people's relationships number two try to
help other
people and then number three you break
number three if you don't move as fast
as you possibly can you break your
Diamond wave vales it's very
interesting so the the thing about the
third set of vales it's all
about uh doing it fast trying to do it
before you die okay and uh he was very
cool he was very interested in it and he
asked us a lot of
questions I think uh Diamond silk
entrepreneur
University uh might have some programs
with them they were very interested
about their University and they want to
work work together okay so here's a list
of things on the outside take your one
day
out uh go for
shelter what that technically means in
and we study it uh we studied it in as
course
number two and uh what it what it really
means is make up your mind about what's
going to help you and what's not going
to help you that's all
uh means
uh the whole essence of taking shelter
is to make a decision about who can help
you or not and that's the essence of
taking shelter or or you can say going
for Refuge right uh it's making a
decision about who can help you and who
cannot help you okay and uh I think you
tend to
as you as you go through life you
eliminate shelters right you're not like
doctor you know doctor's like I don't
know what's going on you're like yeah
thanks but don't forget to
pay you're like okay you know so uh you
start to just you start to narrow down
who can help you who can really help you
okay and that's that's shelter that's
taking Refuge okay uh feeling the wish
wish is the wish for enlightenment I
should become a Buddha it's it's
uh when you go to visit a person who's
going to die tonight and she's got small
children and the children are scared and
the husband is a young man and he's
scared and and uh then you wish you
could do something to really help them
you know and so that's the the wish for
enlightenment whenever you think of that
wish
please remember planets okay and
stepping from planet to planet okay and
that's
mainly what differentiates it from from
other good wishes is the scope the scope
is uh inconceivable the the scope is
unbelievable the scope is literally
walking from planet to planet okay and
you you have that ability right now okay
you already have that ability it's in
your mind you just didn't unlock it you
didn't open it okay everybody in this
room if you haven't done that exercise
walking from planet to planet which
should be enough that we don't have to
do
yoga not really uh just walking from
planet to planet if
if it's something amazing and you have
the capacity now you already have the
capacity you just just need to try okay
you just need to really try and then
after you do it once it's like virginity
okay your whole life has changed you're
a different person and it you never go
back you can never go back and you can
never forget it okay and it's
extremely beautiful okay uh it's
extremely beautiful to walk around life
with that memory in your in your heart
of having walked from planet to planet
to help people okay it's very
very you can do it you can do it at
Diamond Mountain that's what diamond
mountain is for okay you're too busy at
home all right so try to do it while
you're here okay all right um then the
for infinite thoughts uh and there's a
very famous uh we we were studying it
were you there at K uh at shivananda in
Bahamas and they have a version of it uh
the four infinite thoughts and
uh may all living
beings
uh be free of thoughts
of what do you call it
Prejudice that they're people are
normally Prejudice towards their
children they they they they will do
anything to protect their own children
but if the neighbor's children are
having trouble that they might call the
police or they might
not if they're busy they won't okay I've
seen it many many times uh
so may we learn to treat all people the
same and by the way the classic four
infinite thoughts has four variations on
each one okay and it's it's nice to know
them
so wouldn't it be nice if I could not be
Prejudice wouldn't it be nice if I could
treat everybody the
same it should happen that everyone is
uh free of this kind of prejudice
neak I'll take I'll take responsibility
you know I'll try to help everybody to
change and I pray that my teacher will
help me to do that okay so there's the
same formula for all the other ones
okay H wouldn't it be nice if all
people could be happy be happy
[Music]
no it would be nice if everyone could be
free of suffering and the causes of
suffering why did they say
that
huh uh just easy we don't it's okay that
box is kind of scary
uh it's
uh it's to cover all the rich people who
are
naughty okay all the powerful people all
the rich people who are behaving badly
okay uh they don't have D but they have
they don't have suffering right now but
they have the cause of suffering so when
we when we try to remove the suffering
of of all beings we try to remove the
cancer and then we try to remove the
things that people got indicted for but
not guilty yet uh okay like we try to
remove the future problems that they're
going to have because they haven't had
those problems yet they've they've pled
the seeds but they haven't had the
problems the problems haven't ripened
yet so we try to take all of them away
okaya uh wouldn't it be nice if they
could be free of all
suffering it should happen it should
happen I'll take care of it myself yeah
and generally the longer you're in the
Dharma business
the more you realize you got to take
care of things yourself you can't wait
for other people okay just get over it
you know don't sit there expecting other
people to help you
know if the temple is messy clean it up
and and don't wait for other people to
help you especially in a Dharma group I
don't know why but there's a l people to
come and help clean up so you know I
cleaned up for 20 years and my teachers
believe
I just got I just decided okay I'll do
it you know I I won't wait for other
people
okay soul I pray that my teachers will
help me to have the power to help remove
the suffering of people now that third
oneu why don't people all have some kind
of Happiness okay why don't people be
happy uh they should wouldn't it be nice
if happy they should be
happy listen I'll take care of it you
guys can go have breakfast I'll take
care of it okay and that's a very
beautiful attitude for your whole life
okay just get used to it stop
complaining that other people are not
helping you it's a SE old man's secret
okay just take care of it yourself and
you don't have to be what do you call it
frustrated that nobody's helping you
just say okay okay if people help me
okay that'd be nice but I don't expect
it you know okay so my
room what's that I hope my uh by the way
the wording says
L May my angel my llama okay may My
Buddha my Lama help me
okay then what's the last l
unmatched happiness so number three is
May everybody be happy number four is
May everybody have super happy okay
that's easy right super happy so number
three is like I hope everybody gets a
good
coffee my
stepson roast the coffee and bought it
in Mexico or Ecuador or something I hope
you like it okay he's a coffee
roaster uh which is
useful okay uh so the third one is I
hope everyone's happy the fourth one is
I hope everyone has ultimate happiness
not just good coffee good coffee is in
number
three okay amera coffee is in number
four uh deathlessness okay deathlessness
what's the Greek for amerta
nectar nectar neck means death tar means
to be free Tara the goddess Tara means
the one who frees you the Greek for
Freedom comes from Sanskrit it's tar and
neck means death like necrofilia or
something that so nectar nectar means
coffee from
Ecuador
okay or you can say AMTA okay
deathlessness okay all
right then it says a strange thing and
I'll give a $100 okay you ready
yeah me and Rob were desperately trying
to find some more money this morning and
then uh the Vietnamese friends said oh
we have a donation we're like
hey
okay uh so you have to thank the
Vietnamese friends if you win it okay
it says here do the four infinite
thoughts from inside of emptiness from
inside of suchness who can give a good
explanation for
$100 and I I don't personally the reason
I'm asking is I don't have a good one in
my mind right now so I'm hoping you guys
will uh Tim you choose
okay
which thank you very much
no uh so I'll try to explain um first we
need to think that these thoughts are
not coming from their own side okay they
are the seeds ripening also and so um by
think by focusing on this on emptiness
of this thoughts this uh seeds become
super powerful okay and infinite yeah I
like it I mean uh basically when we
[Music]
say and you're trying to
help people who are not there the prayer
the Mantra is may I help people who are
not there okay and that's what it means
okay the people people you're trying to
help are not there what's that mean of
course they're there yes but they take
your $100 I
[Laughter]
mean yes uh the people are not there
from their own side yeah nice okay nice
nice
okay hey Tina is that a $200 answer to a
$100 I think so all
right that's a two that's a $200
[Music]
answer first we hand out the money and
then
[Applause]
we first we hand out the money and then
we fundraise for d
m all right next inem you guys there's
somebody going like this yeah this means
now that you have have prepared the
inside with the one day vales
Etc uh it's time to prepare the outside
okay and we already covered these parts
uh last year but I'm just reviewing them
for you and for myself too okay so
preparing the outside has the following
five
steps next
slide yeah uh so I got this who's arriv
Ral yeah medicine a gang okay it's a
gang it's eight eight Buddhas okay all
right um okay sometimes they say seven
because they don't count our
Buddha shakim but if you count our
Buddha then it's eight okay all right
good uh number one blessing the
land and we're kind of doing that with
our protection markers so you got right
Tim when are they making them
no
sorry anyway normally we make protection
markers and
uh when you do a retreat uh it's good to
put a special marker on your door okay
and at the four directions of your
retreat ctage okay so especially the the
door but also the other three Sid
okay and uh that's a whole ritual it has
a and this is a special
blessing uh that will keep uh negative
influences out of your cabin okay so
it's very good to do when you're on
Retreat and
uh again I'll repeat from yesterday I
don't like
Superstition I I think it's very
destructive in religion uh when people
are are
superstitious I I think it's a bad
idea but uh these are just practical
it's like wearing a mask for covid you
know it works uh it's a real thing and
and I you know I I tried doing Retreat
without it and I found out wow it really
does work you know so uh I really
encourage you to do it okay I really
encourage you to to learn how to make a
protection marker will put them out to
bless the whole property this property
is huge this property is 1,60 Acres how
many hectares is that it's about
three 300 hectares I guess how many moo
is
that it's 2,000 moose I think or
something like that I don't know anyway
it's a lot okay it's huge it's it's
several mountains here and um we we we
protect the whole land we put protection
markers out for the whole land and it's
a it's a beautiful thing and it it works
okay so bless the land all right uh
number two bless the Divine Mansions
then you imagine a beautiful palace and
we're going to your
meditation cabin whether it has hot
water or
not is a rep I'm just kidding uh it
represents a divine Palace okay and you
have to imagine that that you're you're
staying you're not inviting medicine
Buddha gang to
some you know economy cabin in on okay
you're inviting them to a beautiful
palace okay and you have to you have to
picture it that way some cabinets need
more picturing than other
cabinets by the way these cabinets uh
were built with Blood Sweat and Tears
okay uh we didn't have any money and uh
everybody in the three-year Retreat paid
for their own cabin with their own money
and and they built their own cabin and
they all said the all the retreaters
there was over 30 retreaters they all
said we will build a cabin and we'll
donate it after this threeyear Retreat
we'll donate it you know and it was so
cute uh people would be running in here
and saying you got a YouTube video how
to pour cement on the plumbing and
they're like yeah I got one you know and
nobody knew how to build a a cottage you
know and and so it was all
YouTube uh instruction and I remember
the cement especially people uh people
were mixing cement on YouTube videos and
uh somebody came over to me and said my
Plumbing stopped
working my my YouTube Plumbing stopped
working you know and I'm
like did didn't you do some cement work
yesterday and they're like yeah and I
said where did you pour out the extra
cement and they're like down the drain
and I'm like okay
so you've now protected that drain for
the next hundred years you know and
people it was a lot of courage and uh a
lot of lot of hard work and many
disappointments many hard times and they
did it and they I think we had two
cottages on the last day before the
retreat were
not uh passed by the County
Inspector so we purposely invited the
fattest
one because these were the ones at the
top of the hill
uh the
Dome and he came to the bottom of the
hill and he
goes looks
good he never walked up
there and uh we passed and we started
the retreat the next day and that's why
the Dums got cracks in and stuff okay
uh but people worked really really hard
and you should thank them who's who's
here from the first threee
retreat's
[Applause]
yeah thank you for the I'm staying in
her cabin it's quite nice thank you for
that all right uh then arrange uh
Thrones when they say Throne it doesn't
mean a European King's throne uh it
means a teaching platform like this one
okay so uh when you see the word
throne uh you could think of a
traditional teaching platform okay and
you arrange a nice platform for each of
the eight Buddhist okay in your in your
cabin which means take some imagination
because it has to be bigger okay all
right uh what's going to happen on the
Thrones by the
way that's a $300 question
are we in trouble
yet I might have to go to the bank
uh why are we setting up Thrones what's
supposed to H what what's going on what
are these prayers
[Applause]
for you are preparing the seats for your
teachers the Buddhas to show up and
teach you
I it's a good start but it's not 300
bucks what are we doing with the medic
Buddha what's the
purpose
H
what calling their name is a big deal
calling their name is a big big deal why
what we're doing what we're doing with a
medicine Buddhist l in that is preparing
to turn ourselves into the medicine
Buddha and then turning ourselves into
the medicine
Buddha I'm not satisfied yet online guys
online
guys 300 bucks online yeah less less
shipping
[Applause]
charges somebody online why why are we
got these Thrones going up what are we
doing
you want me to go on in this
room okay
sure I guess people online don't like
money those hellsinki people you only
get one chance
okay yeah
okay
Olga Buddha of medicine like direct
connection and kind of open the door for
them to come or
something wow why are we here what
what's what are we doing understanding
The Emptiness of the medicine Buddha
practice by calling their
names
why huh can I
say we are saying their
prayers we are saying their prayers they
made when they were bod satas so and uh
due to those prayers they became Buddhas
and so we do the
same okay cancel the
bed Maran you want to try
Mariana we remember them on their
promises they made for us to help to
always come and
help okay I'm not
satisfied uh they each made a promise to
help living beings and the purpose of
this week the purpose to be here this
week uh the purpose of the sadna and the
the content of the two sutras the two
medicine Buddha sutras the basic content
is please keep your four prayers please
keep your eight prayers please keep your
seven prayers there's a certain number
of prayers for each Buddha right and you
say please honor your
prayers so so please take care of other
people that's all please take care of
other people keep your promise you you
you made so many prayers each one of you
most of them made four some of them made
more okay and you say please keep your
prayers for other people that's the
sutras that's the structure of all the
both sutras okay this sad is
different okay it's very interesting
this sodna is different okay and uh and
that's what I want you to be sensitive
to in the first few days before you go
into your three days retreat in
general the content of the sutras is
please help please keep your promises
for other people okay and in general the
content of this sadna is don't forget
me okay I also and it's not selfish it's
just like you know the citus are cool
but they don't put that much emphasis on
me you know and uh this this sna as you
will see as you read it uh a lot of it
is
identifying problems in your own life
okay identifying problems in your own
life that their prayers cover okay so
it's kind of like you got to know what
their prayers were and then you have to
say by the way I also have this problem
you know I also have this problem and
please help me also okay so the main
emphasis this week and the main emphasis
of your three-day Retreat you will say
please keep your commitments your four
prayers or your eight prayers please
keep the promises that you made to
others but I also have these problems so
there's a big emphasis in this second
medicine Buddha lineage there's a big
emphasis on I also have these problems I
and you try to identify
how you have the problems that are
listed in the sutris okay so so we go
through the prayers again it in in this
sna in the fif we will go through the
same prayers again but you're supposed
to slow down and say I also have this
problem you know and please help me with
that problem okay all right that's the
main difference okay this S as you go
through it it's different from the
sutras the sutras are more General
you're praying for everybody and then
this sodna is going to be a lot of
emphasis on hey I'm I also have these
problems and help me okay all right and
not in a selfish way but just to
recognize that these are not theoretical
prayers for other people they're also
prayers for your own family your own
life okay all right then bless the
offerings uh we went through that
already uh we we bless offerings you're
like giving a few uh
old oranges or
strawberries and
uh but you have to multiply them for you
know there's the eight guys and then
there's they each have like 500 buies
office with them and it gets
expensive okay lots of offerings okay
you can't possibly make offerings for
all of them uh but mentally you can do
it okay so the offerings have to be
multiplied we got buod safas
there okay we got special vote buis saas
in
attendance and you can read about them
in the Sutra okay okay and then uh you
get everything ready so this outer
What's called the outer
preparation is they always say as if you
have an important guest coming to your
home okay as if you have an important
guest coming to your home we took over
Stanley Nelson's house in rron for the
Mixed Nuts
classes and they didn't sleep the night
before because they were trying to make
the house nice and and like that so it's
that kind of thing I tried to give them
the initiation into sloppy Dharma
students who spill coffee on your couch
and
stuff and then you discover the
emptiness of your refrigerator after
they
leave and uh stuff like that but they're
gonna you're gonna experience it don't
be disappointed okay just you know Mom
and Dad don't kick out the kids when
they make a mess right I mean they
should but they
don't all right begging them to come and
then when everything's ready you say
please come okay so the whole room is
nice and everything's prepared and then
you say please come okay then we finish
the outer
preparations uh for fun I want to show
you uh a rock star who was singing in
Asia
recently he's he's from Shenzhen
China he a very popular
singer uh and this is the next step in
our Su okay you
ready
Tim no there's a
video there was a
video
sound
[Music]
yeah not me him
be to
w
[Music]
and I'm afraid to
live it would be
Li
ibody
know
everybody all of
do come back
you
[Music]
[Applause]
oh
[Music]
that's during Stanley
[Applause]
[Music]
song
so
that was uh Max woo that was his
first uh the first event he ever
organized and 6,000 people came so he's
doing pretty good uh the the point is uh
the next step uh you have Part D you
guys the slide there's a slide for Part
D yeah uh we call it the convocation
okay and that's what's the next thing in
the S okay and I was trying to think of
a
convocation and that's
the that's that Stadium you saw okay and
and actually Stanley was singing while
they were doing this thing he was
singing a famous Chinese rock
song and I was supposed to sing with him
and I chickened out and uh he had to do
it on his own and but
uh the the word convocation
in English and in the sadna it should
feel like that and I wanted you to get
the feeling it should feel like
thousands of people are coming okay in
your little meditation room okay it's
going to take a lot of imagination to
increase the capacity of the of the
cabin okay but but uh in the sna it's a
convocation convocation means try to
think of all those seeds and they're
putting out 6,000 seats and they're
getting ready for 6,000 people to come
and try to imagine it like that okay
it's big it I want you to get the scale
in your mind okay uh each Buddha has a
gang with them each Buddha has hundreds
of attendance and helpers with them okay
people who have committed to help them
so should be the retreat Valley is
really
overpopulated by the time you finish
okay and don't don't be cheap okay like
make it big it's a convocation it's a
huge Gathering okay and uh that's part
of this sudden all right and those are
basically a Dharma Army it's basically a
Dharma Army you're inviting a Dharma
Army to come to this world and help
people stop their suffering okay so
don't be don't be shy and don't be
cheap okay lots of seeds
lots of Refreshments you know probably
extra
bathrooms you know okay all right uh
this week uh it has to be generous and
it has to be beautiful and it has to be
like a big party okay and don't don't
put like three Buddhas up on a folding
chair and then go away give up mentally
not like that it has to be a grand party
we call conv location okay work on it
okay work on making it every person
there is a Buddha or a Buddhist suffer
okay everybody in the audience is a
Buddha or a bod okay it's like and these
are the people who are going to help
take away the suffering of this world
and other worlds okay so they are like
an army and you like the general okay
all right so you have to it's a big job
and don't don't be cheap and don't be
small don't be small minded okay oh gu I
can only fit two Buddhas in my room you
know n come
on be be generous and be wide and it by
the way it helps your meditation okay if
your meditation is tight and small
you'll have all these uh long-term
Retreat problems nervous Loom you know
you'll be you might get nervous or
things like that if you got this huge
stadium and thousands of Buddhist and
bonis saas then it makes a big
difference in your meditation your
meditation will be more open and more
free and you won't get all these
meditation obstacles that people get
when they when they start to get a tight
chest or they feel pain in their chest
or in their knees or their back okay you
can't invite 6,000 people in Buddhas and
Buddhist office and feel like you're in
a
closet okay so it's it's all a trick by
the fifth di to open up your mind during
the meditation so you don't get tight
okay so uh go for it and and be be
generous it's a lot of fun okay if it
goes if you really work on it it's it's
really fun it's like organizing I'm sure
Max feels like that the the the day
after he feels like he had a big party
and you know and he did a great job if
you see him you should thank him from
from okay uh all right uh in in part
D uh in the sadna
they they also they don't just honor the
a Buddhas and the bodh satas they
honor uh the entire lineage of the
medicine budha practice in this
world and uh the fifth dilemma was very
careful to identify each person in the
lineage and it was it's a good piece of
work you know if you're interested in in
Buddhism in this planet it's a very fine
piece of work and a difficult piece of
work and he did a good he did a good job
he he basically
identifies every teacher who passed on
this practice and all of their names are
there uh and and it was very difficult
to trace
them uh from the beginning of Buddhism
in in West China in Tibet because of the
uh when Buddhism reached West China a
thousand years ago they didn't even have
an
alphabet they didn't have a written
language uh and they were just hurting
Yaks you know and hunting and they
didn't grow a lot of crops it's too high
they were basically just hunters and and
Yak herders and uh so there's not very
good records of who the early teachers
were and what were they doing and what
were their names and the the fifth
dialam is very careful and he traced the
whole thing back so so it's a very
beautiful list of all the people who
passed on the medicine Buddha teachings
okay and he he did it somehow he he
figured it out and uh it was hard even
to translate because Mo most of those
people are long forgotten you know and
it's very beautiful so appreciate the
lineage there okay all right uh next
item something new is coming okay we
finished reviewing the first 100 pages
of the Sun and now ready to in to
acquaint you with the second 100 pages
so we translated another 100 pages and
then next for next year we'll translate
the last 100 pages okay so you've got
2third of the S now okay and I cut it at
a logical place okay we finished all the
eight Buddhists they they arrive they
start doing their thing and then we
stopped translating okay we just ran out
of time
I could have done more if I had time
okay
so okay I just didn't have time all
right
um all right next
item uh this is called preparing the
inside deeper going deeper on the on the
preparation okay and what what do you
notice
here it seems like a repeat of the
earlier one okay hey we already did
these seven preliminaries by the way
there's only six here why the first one
has
two
okay uh we go back to the seven
preliminaries okay why do we go back to
the seven preliminaries if you study the
S which I'm sure you will do in these
three days since you've saved so much
time not looking at your
phone ever in those three days is okay
just put it away okay uh they have this
great custom in China in
Shenzhen when we give a talk there they
they ask the people to leave their phone
outside and there's a special phone
holder and it's a it's a great invention
and no nobody in the room has a phone
and it's really nice I don't know who
started that but it's really really nice
uh so
anyway now that you don't have a phone
for three days at least you can really
focus on your on these preparations okay
on these seven
preliminaries and this time the there
are not General prostrations and they
are not General offerings this time they
are specifically to the eight medicine
Buddha gang okay seven Buddhists of the
medicine Buddha his six friends and then
our Buddha who's kind of
a
man talent
manager okay talent agent and he he
brings the seven medicine Buddha gang to
to your cabin and he he kind of
organizes everything okay all right uh
then you're going to go through the
normal steps of confessing confessing
try to find
something I like to find fresh bad
Deeds uh I don't like to dwell on Old
bad Deeds that I did in University
anything you did in University you
shouldn't have to think
about uh cuz you were wild in those days
so they went to my university I
don't I mean you put four or
5,000 18 year olds in a in a town
there's going to be some stuff is going
to happen right so uh
anyway I like to confess things I've
done recently in the last 24 hours I'd
rather do a
small mistake mistake that I made in the
last 24 hours than something big I did
20 years ago you should have confessed
those big ones 20 years ago by now okay
we don't want old material for
confession we want fresh
stuff okay and that might mean something
you thought about in class or or you
were irritated at another student here
or something like that there's plenty of
people to be irritated at
here uh and
you can confess something fresh okay
that's my advice okay something in the
last two three days okay if you think
about what's going to hold you back it's
not those grand bad Deeds you did once
in your life okay it's the little ones
that you do every hour that that's what
holds you back okay the big mistakes you
already confessed them hopefully but the
little hour toour mistakes you just they
just pile up so so try to think of a
couple that you did in the class or
something like that okay mistakes made
in the class are especially irritating
to the medicine Buddhists you know hey
you were supposed to have had class
about us and you were thinking about the
person next to you and being irritated
what's wrong with you okay all right uh
rejoicing uh be happy again my
experience is that
people tend to not rejoice very well I
think almost every human being is uh
even the Arrogant or the proud people
still people are shy to admit that they
did something good you know uh I think
all of us and all of you have done very
good things in your life you've taken
care of many people you've done very
kind things in your life and you
continue to do kind things in your life
and and and you really have to work hard
to think about it okay and don't don't
uh ignore it okay it's an
important step in this Retreat okay if
you uh try to be Noble or something
modest and you don't admit the good
things you've done uh it's a mistake
it's a serious mistake okay so give it
some real time give it some real thought
you know you you're here it's hard to
get here it's expensive to get here uh
it's difficult there's traveling like
that is difficult and you're here okay
even if you're a terrible person you're
here okay so you can Rejoice about that
okay like I'm I'm a really stupid person
but I made it here you know and uh
really uh in my experience you know I'm
an old uh meditator and I have done many
many years of retreat
total uh and uh I think the problem is
that people
don't uh Rejoice enough about the good
things they're doing okay and it's not
Pride okay it's not Pride to Rejoice
about your
own uh spiritual work even if it's lousy
and
lazy uh it's still great okay it's still
really really great and the Buddhist are
really happy that you're here you know
there's one serious Retreat Center in
the whole United States to do this kind
of retreat and you're at it and uh
hopefully if we're successful there will
be thousands of retreat centers like
this but so far it hasn't happened okay
and you're there you made it okay you
made it at the beginning so in Tibet you
know there came and in China there came
to be thousands and thousands of retreat
centers uh but we're just starting here
okay all right if you're here you must
be
special or just in the wrong place I
don't know
okay okay and uh please Rejoice okay it
will help your meditation Al it's not
just for Pride or something like that
it'll open up your heart and your
retreat will be much more successful
okay Stanley's working on Innovation
Retreats here creativity Retreats for
artists or business people or and I
think that's an a really
vital training that new people who come
here should be trained in rejoicing
properly about the good things they've
done and that may be one of the most
important things we can teach people
when they get here if they're going to
do a we're talking about doing
Innovation Retreats or creativity
Retreats here okay and by as I said
yesterday uh a lot of
my business success which was huge I
mean I didn't know anything about
business I didn't like business I didn't
want to do business my teacher forced me
to do
business really forced me and I did not
want to do it and uh but but the
Retreats were my secret weapon for my
business and and it
and and it did become the largest
company of its kind in the world and and
either that's just stupid good luck or
the Retreats did something okay and I
think you should think about it okay you
can in your own life whatever you want
to
do uh use your retreat time to think
about what you want to do with your life
and what you want to do when you get out
of retreat okay don't waste your time
here
okay don't like look at the calendar and
hope that the three days goes fast you
know so you can get back to your honey
what's your honey P your
phone uh so just uh use the time and I
acip all was created in these Retreat
centers okay the idea for the database
the idea for the search program the
design of the search program all these
translations they they came from these
Retreats okay so so use the time and you
are very very free during the three
days
to to use your
imagination about where do you want to
take your life now you know this is a a
pause in your life for three days and
you don't get pauses in your life life
tends to just go really fast suddenly
you're old man you know you know whoa
what happened you know and uh the
retreat is a is a beautiful time I
remember shaing said uh she and Stanley
came down here for 10 days they said we
want to know we want to think about our
future Gish I said go to Diamond
Mountain do a 10-day Retreat and uh she
came out and she said I want to build a
university and I'm like yeah okay and uh
and she did uh and it's a it's it's a
major project it's like 20 $330 million
project and uh she's doing it and
uh
[Laughter]
yeah if I run short on handy out cash
I'll I'll contact you
uh but use use the time don't waste your
time okay yeah it's a pause in your life
it's a unique pause in your life you
never pause your life like this and
three days is enough to have some real
uh plans for your future so
listen listen to The Cosmic voice right
it's the medicine Buddha whispering to
you I think you to study University
you're like
what so keep your ears open and keep
your heart open and and uh don't think
about your phone okay but uh I would say
in my own case and I know shoping other
people uh a lot of our inspiration for
our whole life has come here at Diamond
Mountain we we heard messages here that
we we were too busy to listen to them in
Shenzhen or or
Rimrock okay Rimrock is too big and busy
right so
uh keep your ears open for those three
days and listen for suggestions about
what where to take your life and many
many people who did Retreat here have
had amazing life after that okay so try
to keep your ears open okay and that's
that's a practice of listening my wife
says I have a problem with
it probably she says I tend to talk all
day and I don't listen
much uh but uh listen during this three
days listen see if you get any good
suggestions for your life okay that's
the purpose of retreat okay Tim what's
the schedule what am I supposed to be
doing uh is there a Q&A
or what time does this class 10 minutes
10 minutes in 10 minutes let's do Q&A uh
so that's all I mean uh we we have
discussed uh part of the medicine Buddha
practice actually it's the one warm up
and the invitation you are setting up
this huge chairs and you're setting up
this huge place and we just invited all
the guests to come and now it's time for
the main event and we'll talk about that
next okay uh this
sadna is
unique compared to the two sutras of
medicine Buddha in that instead of
saying please help all the
people you just change it slightly and
you say please help all the people
including me okay you know like that
okay and this sun is very is very clear
it's very clear that the fifth D Lama
wants you to ask for help directly and
and we're going to go through the actual
prayers of the medicine Buddhas and see
how each one applies to me okay we're
going to go through the prayers not all
we don't have time to do all of them but
we'll go through each of the a classical
medicine B of prayers and we'll pray for
personal help this this way me too me
too okay all right Tim any Q&A from
maybe on online
people so do you want a light question
or do you want a hard question I like
hard questions okay all right here we
go g this comes from someone named Elva
and they
say what is the difference between the
nature of seeing emptiness directly and
meditations like the four spaces and the
Lion's dance
meditation yeah okay good um what the
difference between uh meditation
practice like the meditation on the four
kinds of space or the the lion dance
meditation and what's the difference
between those two and say a direct
perception emptiness in meditation
um there's a meditative platform called
uh
say and that's a particular
meditative level okay it's it's it's
it's where your mind goes deep deep
enough to see emptiness
okay uh and it's an interesting thing if
you don't go that deep you won't see
emptiness okay that I call it the
platform it's from that
platform that's the only
meditation level from which you can see
emptiness directly so if you don't get
that deep you'll never see emptiness
because your mind is not deep enough and
if you go deeper you won't see emptiness
either it's very interesting okay and we
don't talk about that much okay but 99%
of people can't get that deep they don't
meditate enough uh and
then uh 1% 2% they go too deep and they
they stop thinking about anything okay
so it's kind of like a a deep meditation
but where you can still think somehow
okay and you don't want to go deeper
than that so you go to a certain level
you stop and you can see emptiness at
that level
um and you get used to going there you
have to get used to going there okay uh
there's a very
very big instruction you you have to to
see emptiness directly you have to be
able to meditate for one hour without
stopping and without distraction and
it's it's difficult okay and I'm not
talking about preliminaries My
Confession takes 59 minutes I only have
I only have one
minute you know so it's not like that
after you finish the preliminaries 60
minutes okay uh okay and uh there's a
very very easy way to reach it uh and
but it took me many years to figure it
out and
uh uh start with 10 minutes okay never
if you have if you're not meditating
daily start with 10 minutes if if you uh
broke your meditation because you were
really busy before you came to retreat
start again start over at 10 minutes
okay and don't be shy about it be proud
about it I'm not a kopa what's Koopa
idiot I'm not an idiot I know I have to
start over why cuz I didn't meditate for
3 weeks before I got here or three
months or three years or whatever okay
so be wise enough to start over Okay and
and that's 10 minutes okay so 10 minutes
of deep
focus and then once a week add one
minute okay and if you go faster than
that you're wrong something's wrong okay
you're not really
meditating okay if you try to increase
two minutes a week or three minutes a
week you you will fail I guarantee you
will fail Okay add one minute per week
and and I'm not shy about it you know my
wife says are you going to meditate
today I say I finished and she says well
you only in there for 10 minutes I'm
like yeah I'm starting
over and uh
you know that's I do it all the time and
and just you know do it that way okay
there's 52 weeks in a year 10 plus 52 is
62 you got two extra
minutes okay in one year you got two
extra minutes so do it that way okay and
uh you'll be able so those other
meditations the force based meditation
you can do a 10-minute Force based
meditation you cannot do a direct
perception The Emptiness meditation in
10 minutes it has to be one hour if you
never ever reach an hour you will never
ever see emptiness directly it's up to
you it's up to you you basically get one
chance every million
years okay you basically get a chance
like this every million years so if you
if you don't feel like it or your
phone's too
important that's your decision okay you
get a CH like this every million years
or something okay and you know actually
it's worse than that so okay so uh
that's how you can do a force basic
meditation you can do a line stance in
10 minutes you cannot do a direct
perception emptiness in 10 minutes
that's on
cool so we have another question from
Ryan I believe it's the Ryan who lives
in
California um and this I think is a cool
question so up until this point our
lineage seems to emphasize highly
emphasize the study of logic all the
lists the five this the seven that part
one of part three you know something
like that um and then at some point when
we start into the higher
teachings um he says he feels like
there's a shift away from logic and more
of a focus on the body in the
relationship of the energies in the
body so he says he feel feels a shift
away from wanting to practice logic and
in practicing the way that emptiness
affects his thoughts and energies in his
body so the question is can you talk
about this and how can I trust what I'm
experiencing in my body versus a logical
understanding of things yeah cool
um you have two tools at your disposal
you have two perceptual tools that your
disposal number one is your direct
perceptions you know taste see smell
okay those those direct perceptions you
have those tools that's part of your
toolkit
okay and that can only be
applied to gross physical objects okay
your your five senses the heart sura
[Music]
says you have five senses your five
senses if you if you didn't have
anything else I think you would be kind
of like a a rabbit at Diamond Mountain
okay they they have very welldeveloped
sense Powers they survive by hearing
coyotes sneaking up behind them you so
their sense powers are very are very
clear and sharp okay but a sense power
can only see a physical object it cannot
understand a concept your sense your
five senses cannot understand the
concept they cannot okay for that you
need logic okay all all all deeper
Concepts all deeper truths are at a
different level of
reality and they can only be seen by
Logic you know and I'm not talking about
you know some German University where
they talk about logic and they're
extremely boring
people I'm I'm
sorry just certain German univers yeah
uh I'm not talking about that I'm
talking about you know is there a
reasonable chance you're going to get a
green drink this
morning uh you are calculating it in
your mind calculation is logic okay all
perceptions of deeper
reality are are are dependent on logic
we don't call it logic you don't think
about it as logic but most of how you
survive in the world is logic okay you
think about what's possible you think
about what can happen you think about
what's the chances and then you take an
action right so all all OB all obvious
reality is perceived with your senses
all deeper reality requires logic okay
and it doesn't mean that you sit there
and and you
know it's not like that it's deeper
thinking call it deeper thinking okay so
I would I I would let go of the word
Logic the the school that we talked
about yesterday and that was a unique
class because you went to the first line
of a 25 year study and you went to the
last line of a 25 year study in one
class and uh no nobody ever does that uh
so you you you must develop those skills
to see emptiness directly you and to
practice the higher teachings vadana
Diamond way completely impossible
without logic totally impossible just
you the higher teachings are are not not
more cinnamon
rolls although I wish they were they are
deeper realities that you can only see
with logic so so the deeper you go in
the higher teachings the deeper you have
to go in the study of logic and it's and
it's fun you know and it's it's
incredibly satisfying it's almost as
good as a cinnamon roll from Peach Tree
Cafe okay it's it's a it's a way of life
it's not a you don't study a logic book
and stop you know you you spend your
whole
life learning how to think okay it's a
study how to think and it's amazing it's
a it's a miracle okay and if you do it
daily if you have a little bit of uh if
you do a little bit of exercise every
day about how to think your thinking
will get more and more powerful
as you get older okay you reach 7 years
old your thinking is 10 times stronger
than it was last year and it's
unbelievable you can do unbelievable
stuff uh it's really cool it's really
amazing and I don't think you can
understand
Tantra uh or or higher teachings without
it it's it's not possible and and nobody
in the tradition would say that you
could uh so it's do you also add
uh physical practices yes yeah
pranayama uh different kinds of Pama ASA
practice uh all the creas that we taught
in YSI classes you do add you add those
uh but a lot of the purpose of them is
to increase your logic ability a lot of
the purpose to do ASA practice pranama
practice
creus uh is to increase your logic
ability the purpose of the physical
practices is to increase your ability to
think okay
cool all right